مَا يَنظُرُونَ إِلَّا صَيْحَةً وَاحِدَةً تَأْخُذُهُمْ وَهُمْ يَخِصِّمُونَ - 36:49
They do not await except one blast which will seize them while they are disputing.
فَلَا يَسْتَطِيعُونَ تَوْصِيَةً وَلَا إِلَىٰ أَهْلِهِمْ يَرْجِعُونَ - 36:50
And they will not be able [to give] any instruction, nor to their people can they return.
وَنُفِخَ فِي الصُّورِ فَإِذَا هُم مِّنَ الْأَجْدَاثِ إِلَىٰ رَبِّهِمْ يَنسِلُونَ - 36:51
And the Horn will be blown; and at once from the graves to their Lord they will hasten.
قَالُوا يَا وَيْلَنَا مَن بَعَثَنَا مِن مَّرْقَدِنَا ۜ ۗ
They will say, "O woe to us! Who has raised us up from our sleeping place?"
هَٰذَا مَا وَعَدَ الرَّحْمَٰنُ وَصَدَقَ الْمُرْسَلُونَ - 36:52
[The reply will be], "This is what the Most Merciful had promised, and the messengers told the truth."
إِن كَانَتْ إِلَّا صَيْحَةً وَاحِدَةً فَإِذَا هُمْ جَمِيعٌ لَّدَيْنَا مُحْضَرُونَ - 36:53
It will not be but one blast, and at once they are all brought present before Us.
فَالْيَوْمَ لَا تُظْلَمُ نَفْسٌ شَيْئًا وَلَا تُجْزَوْنَ إِلَّا مَا كُنتُمْ تَعْمَلُونَ - 36:54
So today no soul will be wronged at all, and you will not be recompensed except for what you used to do.
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the cursed Satan
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the name of Allah, The All-Merciful, The Ever-Merciful
وَآيَةٌ لَّهُمْ أَنَّا حَمَلْنَا ذُرِّيَّتَهُمْ فِي الْفُلْكِ الْمَشْحُونِ - 36:41
And a sign for them is that We carried their forefathers in a laden ship.
وَخَلَقْنَا لَهُم مِّن مِّثْلِهِ مَا يَرْكَبُونَ - 36:42
And We created for them from the likes of it that which they ride.
وَإِن نَّشَأْ نُغْرِقْهُمْ فَلَا صَرِيخَ لَهُمْ
And if We should will, We could drown them; then no one responding to a cry would there be for them,
وَلَا هُمْ يُنقَذُونَ - 36:43
nor would they be saved
إِلَّا رَحْمَةً مِّنَّا وَمَتَاعًا إِلَىٰ حِينٍ - 36:44
Except as a mercy from Us and provision for a time.
وَإِذَا قِيلَ لَهُمُ اتَّقُوا مَا بَيْنَ أَيْدِيكُمْ وَمَا خَلْفَكُمْ لَعَلَّكُمْ تُرْحَمُونَ - 36:45
But when it is said to them, "Beware of what is before you and what is behind you; perhaps you will receive mercy... "
وَمَا تَأْتِيهِم مِّنْ آيَةٍ مِّنْ آيَاتِ رَبِّهِمْ إِلَّا كَانُوا عَنْهَا مُعْرِضِينَ - 36:46
And no sign comes to them from the signs of their Lord except that they are from it turning away.
وَإِذَا قِيلَ لَهُمْ أَنفِقُوا مِمَّا رَزَقَكُمُ اللَّهُ قَالَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا
And when it is said to them, "Spend from that which Allah has provided for you," those who disbelieve say ...
قَالَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا لِلَّذِينَ آمَنُوا أَنُطْعِمُ مَن لَّوْ يَشَاءُ اللَّهُ أَطْعَمَهُ
those who disbelieve say to those who believe, "Should we feed one whom, if Allah had willed, He would have fed?
إِنْ أَنتُمْ إِلَّا فِي ضَلَالٍ مُّبِينٍ - 36:47
You are not but in clear error."
وَيَقُولُونَ مَتَىٰ هَٰذَا الْوَعْدُ إِن كُنتُمْ صَادِقِينَ - 36:48
And they say, "When is this promise, if you should be truthful?"
مَا يَنظُرُونَ إِلَّا صَيْحَةً وَاحِدَةً تَأْخُذُهُمْ وَهُمْ يَخِصِّمُونَ - 36:49
They do not await except one blast which will seize them while they are disputing.
فَلَا يَسْتَطِيعُونَ تَوْصِيَةً وَلَا إِلَىٰ أَهْلِهِمْ يَرْجِعُونَ - 36:50
And they will not be able [to give] any instruction, nor to their people can they return.
وَنُفِخَ فِي الصُّورِ فَإِذَا هُم مِّنَ الْأَجْدَاثِ إِلَىٰ رَبِّهِمْ يَنسِلُونَ - 36:51
And the Horn will be blown; and at once from the graves to their Lord they will hasten.
قَالُوا يَا وَيْلَنَا مَن بَعَثَنَا مِن مَّرْقَدِنَا ۜ ۗ
They will say, "O woe to us! Who has raised us up from our sleeping place?"
هَٰذَا مَا وَعَدَ الرَّحْمَٰنُ وَصَدَقَ الْمُرْسَلُونَ - 36:52
[The reply will be], "This is what the Most Merciful had promised, and the messengers told the truth."
إِن كَانَتْ إِلَّا صَيْحَةً وَاحِدَةً فَإِذَا هُمْ جَمِيعٌ لَّدَيْنَا مُحْضَرُونَ - 36:53
It will not be but one blast, and at once they are all brought present before Us.
فَالْيَوْمَ لَا تُظْلَمُ نَفْسٌ شَيْئًا وَلَا تُجْزَوْنَ إِلَّا مَا كُنتُمْ تَعْمَلُونَ - 36:54
So today no soul will be wronged at all, and you will not be recompensed except for what you used to do.
إِنَّ أَصْحَابَ الْجَنَّةِ الْيَوْمَ فِي شُغُلٍ فَاكِهُونَ - 36:55
Indeed the companions of Paradise, that Day, will be amused in [joyful] occupation -
هُمْ وَأَزْوَاجُهُمْ فِي ظِلَالٍ عَلَى الْأَرَائِكِ مُتَّكِئُونَ - 36:56
They and their spouses - in shade, reclining on adorned couches.
لَهُمْ فِيهَا فَاكِهَةٌ وَلَهُم مَّا يَدَّعُونَ - 36:57
For them therein is fruit, and for them is whatever they request [or wish]
سَلَامٌ قَوْلًا مِّن رَّبٍّ رَّحِيمٍ - 36:58
[And] "Peace," a word from a Merciful Lord.
وَامْتَازُوا الْيَوْمَ أَيُّهَا الْمُجْرِمُونَ - 36:59
[Then He will say], "But stand apart today, you criminals.
أَلَمْ أَعْهَدْ إِلَيْكُمْ يَا بَنِي آدَمَ أَن لَّا تَعْبُدُوا الشَّيْطَانَ ۖ إِنَّهُ لَكُمْ عَدُوٌّ مُّبِينٌ - 36:60
Did I not enjoin upon you, O children of Adam, that you not worship Satan - [for] indeed, he is to you a clear enemy -
وَأَنِ اعْبُدُونِي ۚ هَٰذَا صِرَاطٌ مُّسْتَقِيمٌ - 36:61
And that you worship [only] Me? This is a straight path.
وَلَقَدْ أَضَلَّ مِنكُمْ جِبِلًّا كَثِيرًا ۖ أَفَلَمْ تَكُونُوا تَعْقِلُونَ - 36:62
And he had already led astray from among you much of creation, so did you not use reason?
هَٰذِهِ جَهَنَّمُ الَّتِي كُنتُمْ تُوعَدُونَ - 36:63
This is the Hellfire which you were promised.
اصْلَوْهَا الْيَوْمَ بِمَا كُنتُمْ تَكْفُرُونَ - 36:64
[Enter to] burn therein today for what you used to deny."
الْيَوْمَ نَخْتِمُ عَلَىٰ أَفْوَاهِهِمْ وَتُكَلِّمُنَا أَيْدِيهِمْ
That Day, We will seal over their mouths, and their hands will speak to Us,
وَتُكَلِّمُنَا أَيْدِيهِمْ وَتَشْهَدُ أَرْجُلُهُم بِمَا كَانُوا يَكْسِبُونَ - 36:65
and their hands will speak to Us, and their feet will testify about what they used to earn.
وَلَوْ نَشَاءُ لَطَمَسْنَا عَلَىٰ أَعْيُنِهِمْ فَاسْتَبَقُوا الصِّرَاطَ فَأَنَّىٰ يُبْصِرُونَ - 36:66
And if We willed, We could have obliterated their eyes, and they would race to [find] the path, and how could they see?
وَلَوْ نَشَاءُ لَمَسَخْنَاهُمْ عَلَىٰ مَكَانَتِهِمْ
And if We willed, We could have deformed them, [paralyzing them] in their places
فَمَا اسْتَطَاعُوا مُضِيًّا وَلَا يَرْجِعُونَ - 36:67
so they would not be able to proceed, nor could they return.
وَمَن نُّعَمِّرْهُ نُنَكِّسْهُ فِي الْخَلْقِ ۖ أَفَلَا يَعْقِلُونَ - 36:68
And he to whom We grant long life We reverse in creation; so will they not understand?
وَمَا عَلَّمْنَاهُ الشِّعْرَ وَمَا يَنبَغِي لَهُ ۚ إِنْ هُوَ إِلَّا ذِكْرٌ وَقُرْآنٌ مُّبِينٌ - 36:69
And We did not give Muhammad, knowledge of poetry, nor is it befitting for him. It is not but a message and a clear Qur'an
لِّيُنذِرَ مَن كَانَ حَيًّا وَيَحِقَّ الْقَوْلُ عَلَى الْكَافِرِينَ - 36:70
To warn whoever is alive and justify the word against the disbelievers.